<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-farrell-etm-00">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="etm">We're gonna need a bigger threat model</title>

<author initials="S." surname="Farrell" fullname="Stephen Farrell">
<organization>Trinity College Dublin</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>stephen.farrell@cs.tcd.ie</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2019" month="April" day="20"/>

<area>Network Working Group</area>
<workgroup></workgroup>
<keyword></keyword>


<abstract>
<t>We argue that an expanded threat model is needed for Internet protocol development
as protocol endpoints can no longer be considered to be generally trustworthy
for any general definition of &quot;trustworthy.&quot;
</t>
<t>This draft will be a submission to the DEDR IAB workshop.
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>[[There's a github repo for this -- issues and PRs are welcome there.
<eref target="https://github.com/sftcd/etm"/> ]]
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC3552"/>, Section 3 defines an &quot;Internet Threat Model&quot; which has been
commonly used when developing Internet protocols.  That assumes that &quot;the
end-systems engaging in a protocol exchange have not themselves been
compromised.&quot; RFC 3552 is a formal part of of the IETF's process as it is also
BCP72.
</t>
<t>Since RFC 3552 was written, we have seen a greater emphasis on considering
privacy and <xref target="RFC6973"/> provides privacy guidance for protocol developers. RFC
6973 is not a formal BCP, but appears to have been useful for protocol
developers as it is referenced by 38 later RFCs at the time of
<eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6973/referencedby/">writing</eref>.
</t>
<t>BCP188, <xref target="RFC7258"/> subsequently recognised pervasive monitoring as a
particular kind of attack and has also been relatively widely referenced (39
RFCs at the time of
<eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7258/referencedby/">writing</eref>). To date,
perhaps most documents referencing BCP188 have considered state-level or
in-network adversaries.
</t>
<t>In this document, we argue that we need to epxand our threat model to
acknowledge that today many applications are themselves rightly considered
potential adversaries for at least some relevant actors. We also argue that
not recognising this reality causes Internet protocol designs to sometimes
fail to protect the systems and users who depend on those.
</t>
<t>Discussion related to expanding our concept of threat-model ought not (but
perhaps inevitably will) involve discussion of weakening how confidentiality is
provided in Internet protocols. Whilst it may superficially seem to be the case
that allowing in-network interception could allow detection of adversarial
application behaviours, such a position is clearly mistaken once one notes that
adding middleboxes that can themselves be adverserial cannot be a solution for
adversarial code. It is also the case that the IETF has consensus on
this topic, as noted in <xref target="RFC2404"/> and BCP 200 <xref target="RFC1984"/>.
</t>
<t>It is unclear whether or not the IETF can be expected to reach rough consensus
on a description of such a new threat model, but we further argue that ignoring
this aspect of deployed reality cannot may not well for Internet protocol
development.
</t>
<t>Absent such an expanded threat
model, we expect to see a continued mismatch between expectaions and the
deployment reality for some Internet protocols.
</t>
<t>This internet-draft is a submission to the IAB's DEDR
<eref target="https://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/dedr-workshop/">workshop</eref> and is not
intended to become an RFC.
</t>
<t>We are saddened by, and apologise for, the somewhat dystopian impression that
this document may impart - hopefully, there's a bit of hope at the end;-)
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="examples-of-deliberate-adversarial-behaviour-in-applications" title="Examples of deliberate adversarial behaviour in applications">
<t>In this section we describe a few documented examples of deliberate adversarial
behaviour by applications that could affect Internet protocol development.  The
adversarial behaviours described below involve various kinds of attack, varying
from simlple fraud, to credential theft, surveillance and contributing to DDoS
attacks.  This is not intended to be a comprehensive nor complete survey, but
to motivate us to consider deliberate adversarial behaviour by applicaions.
Finally, we note that while we have these examples of deliberate adversarial
behaviour, there are also many example of applciations deveopers doing their
best to protect the security and privacy of their users or customers.
</t>

<section anchor="malware-in-curated-application-stores" title="Malware in curated application stores">
<t>Despite the best efforts of curators, so-called AppStores have frequently been
(ab)used to distribute malware of many kinds and one recent study <xref target="curated"/>
claims that simple obfuscation enables malware to avoid detection. Given the
scale of these deployments, even a small percentage of malware-infected
applictions can affect a huge numbers of people.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="virtual-private-networks-vpns" title="Virtual private networks (VPNs)">
<t>Virtual private networks (VPNs) are supposed to hide user traffic to various
degrees depending on the particular technology chosen by the VPN provider.
However, not all VPNs do what they say, some for example misrepresenting the
countries in which they provide vantage points. <xref target="vpns"/>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="compromised-home-networks" title="Compromised (home) networks">
<t>What we normally might consider networking appliances do also run applications
that can end up being adversarial, for example DNS and DHCP attacks from home
routers, or other devices in the home. One study [home] reports on a 2011
attack that affected 4.5 million DSL modems in Brazil.  The absence of software
update <xref target="RFC8240"/> has been a major cause of these issues and rises to the
level that considering this as intentional behaviour is warranted.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="web-browsers" title="Web browsers">
<t>Tracking of users in order to support advertising based business models is
ubiquitous on the Internet today.  HTTP header fields (such as cookies) are
commonly used for such tracking, as are structures within the content of HTTP
responses such as links to 1x1 pixel images and (ab)use of Javascript APIs
offered by browsers.  <xref target="tracking"/>
</t>
<t>While some web users may be sanguine about this kind of tracking in some
contexts, other users consider this behaviour unwelcome, when or if they are
informed that it happens, [attitude] though the evidence here seems somewhat
harder to interpret and many studies (that we have found to date) involve small
numbers of users.  Historically, browsers have not made this kind of tracking
visible and have supported it by default, though some recent browser versions
are starting to enable visibility and blocking of tracking. Browsers are also
increasingly imposing more stringent requirements on plug-ins for security
reasons.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="web-sites" title="Web sites">
<t>Many web sites today provide some form of privacy policy and terms of service,
that are mostly unread. <xref target="unread"/> This implies that, legal fiction aside,
users of those sites have not in reality agreed to the specific terms published
and so users are therefore highly exposed to being exploited by web sites, for
example <xref target="cambridge"/> is a recent well-publicised case where a service provider
abused the data of 87 million users via a partnership.  While many web site
operators claim that they care deeply about privacy, it seems prudent to assume
that some do not in fact care about user privacy, or at least not in ways with
which many of their users would agree. And of course, today's web sites are
actually mostly fairly complex web applications and are no longer static sets
of HTML files, so calling these &quot;web sites&quot; is perhaps a misnomer, but
considered as web applications, it seems clear that many such exist that are
adversarial.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="tracking-bugs-in-mail" title="Tracking bugs in mail">
<t>Some mail user agents (MUAs) render HTML content by default (some not allowing
this to be turned off, perhaps particularly MUAs on mobile devices) and thus
enable the same kind of adversarial tracking as is seen on the web. Such
intentional tracking is also seen many times per day by email users - in one
study <xref target="mailbug"/> the authors estimated that 62% of PII leakage to third
parties was intentional, for example if leaked data included a hash of the
recipient email address.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="smart-televisions" title="Smart televisions">
<t>There have been examples of so-called &quot;smart&quot; televisions spying on their
owners <eref target="https://www.welivesecurity.com/2013/11/22/lg-admits-that-its-smart-tvs-have-been-watching-users-and-transmitting-data-without-consent/">without
permission</eref>
and one survey of user attitudes <xref target="smarttv"/> found &quot;broad agreement was that it
is unacceptable for the data to be repurposed or shared&quot; although the level of
user understanding may be questionable.  What is clear though is that such
devices generally have not provided controls for their owners that would allow
them to meaningfully make a decision as to whether or not they want to share
such data.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="socalled-internet-of-things" title="So-called Internet of things">
<t>Many so-called Internet of Things (IoT) devices (&quot;so-called&quot; since all devices
were already things:-) have been found extremely deficient when their security
and privacy aspects were analysed, for example children's toys. <xref target="toys"/> While
in some cases this may be due to incompetence rather than deliberate, the
levels of incompetence frequently seen imply that it is valid to consider such
cases as not being accidental.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="inadvertent-adversarial-behaviours" title="Inadvertent adversarial behaviours">
<t>Not all adversarial behaviour by applications is deliberate, some is likely due
to carelessness and/or due to erroneous assumptions about the environments in
which applications (now) run.  For the sake of brevity, we simply list some
such cases:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Application abuse for command and control, for example,
use of IRC or apache logs for <eref target="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/100577/creating-botnet-cc-server-what-architecture-should-i-use-irc-http">malware command and control</eref></t>
<t>Carelessly <eref target="https://businessinsights.bitdefender.com/worst-amazon-breaches">leaky buckets</eref>, for
example, lots of Amazon S3 leaks showing that careless admins can too easily
cause application server data to become available to adversaries</t>
<t>Virtualisation exposing secrets, for example <eref target="https://www.us-cert.gov/ncas/alerts/TA18-004A">Meltdown and Spectre</eref>
and similar side-channels</t>
<t>Compromised badly-maintained web sites, for example that
have lead to massive online <eref target="https://haveibeenpwned.com/Passwords">databases of passwords</eref></t>
<t>Supply-chain attacks, for example the <eref target="https://www.zdnet.com/article/how-hackers-stole-millions-of-credit-card-records-from-target/">Target attack</eref></t>
<t>Breaches of major service providers, that many of us might have assumed would be
sufficiently capable to be the best large-scale &quot;Identity providers&quot;, for example:
<list style="symbols">
<t>3 billion accounts: <eref target="https://www.wired.com/story/yahoo-breach-three-billion-accounts/">yahoo</eref></t>
<t>many millions at risk: <eref target="https://www.zdnet.com/article/us-telcos-caught-selling-your-location-data-again-senator-demands-new-laws/">telcos selling location data</eref></t>
<t>50 million accounts: <eref target="https://www.cnet.com/news/facebook-breach-affected-50-million-people/">facebook</eref></t>
<t>14 million accounts: <eref target="https://www.zdnet.com/article/millions-verizon-customer-records-israeli-data/">verizon</eref></t>
<t>&quot;hundreds of thousands&quot; of accounts: <eref target="https://www.wsj.com/articles/google-exposed-user-data-feared-repercussions-of-disclosing-to-public-1539017194">google</eref></t>
<t>unknown numbers, some email content exposed: <eref target="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/ywyz3x/hackers-could-read-your-hotmail-msn-outlook-microsoft-customer-support">microsoft</eref></t>
</list></t>
<t>Breaches of smaller service providers: Too many to enumerate, sadly</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="possible-directions-for-an-expanded-threat-model" title="Possible directions for an expanded threat model">
<t>We don't claim to have any definitive solutions or answers but
simply call out some potential directions that could be
explored at the DEDR workshop and thereafter.
</t>

<section anchor="develop-a-bcp-for-privacy-considerations" title="Develop a BCP for privacy considerations">
<t>It may be time for the IETF to develop a BCP for privacy
considerations, possibly starting from <xref target="RFC6973"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="consider-the-user-perspective" title="Consider the user perspective">
<t><xref target="I-D.nottingham-for-the-users"/> argues that, in relevant cases where there are
conflicting requirements, the &quot;IETF considers end users as its highest priority
concern.&quot; It seems that doing so is consistent with the
expanded threat model being argued for here.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="consider-abusecases-as-well-as-usecases" title="Consider ABuse-cases as well as use-cases">
<t>Protocol developers and those implementing and deploying Internet
technologies are typically most interested in a few specific
use-cases for which they need solutions. Expanding our threat
model to include adversarial application behaviours [abusecases] seems likely
to call for significant attention to be paid to potential
abuses of whatever new or re-purposed technology is being
considered.
</t>
<t>Protocol extensibility mechanisms may constitute a
particular vector for abuse-cases, given that designers
cannot fully analyse their impact at the time a new
protocol is defined or standardised. One might consider then that
a lack of extensibility could be a virtue for some
new protocols, in contrast to earlier assumptions.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="isolation" title="Isolation">
<t>Sophisticated users can deal with some potentially adversarial behaviours in
client applications by using different instances of such applications, for
example, differently configured web browsers for use in different contexts.
Applications (including web browsers) and operating systems are also
building in isolation via use of different processes or sandboxing.
<vspace/>
Protocol artefacts that relate to uses of such isolation
mechanisms might be worth considering.
</t>
<t>To an extent, the IETF has already recognised some of these issues as being
in-scope, e.g.  when considering the linkability issues with mechanisms such as
TLS session tickets, or QUIC connection identifiers.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="minimise" title="Minimise">
<t>As recommended in <xref target="RFC6973"/> data minimisation and
additional encryption are likely
to be helpful - if applications don't ever see data,
or a cleartext form of data, then they should have a
harder time misbehaving. Similarly, not adding new
long-term identifiers, and not exposing existing ones,
would seem helpful.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="transparency" title="Transparency">
<t>Certificate transparency (CT) <xref target="RFC6962"/> has been an effective
countermeasure for X.509 certificate mis-issuance, which is
a known application layer misbehaviour. While the context
in which CT operates is very constrained (essentially to the public CAs
trusted by web browsers), similar approaches could be
useful for other protocols or technologies.
</t>
<t>In addition, legislative requirements such as those
imposed by the GDPR for <eref target="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-15-gdpr/">subject access to data</eref>
could lead to a desire to handle internal data structures
and databases in ways that are reminiscent of
CT, though clearly with signifnant authorisation
being required and without the append-only nature
of a CT log.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sameorigin-policy" title="Same-Origin Policy">
<t>The Same-Origin Policy (SOP) [?@RFC6464] may provide an example of
how going beyond the RFC 3552 threat model can be useful.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="greasing" title="Greasing">
<t>The TLS protocol <xref target="RFC8446"/> now supports the use of
GREASE <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-grease"/> as a way to mitigate
on-path ossification. While this technique is not
likely to prevent any deliberate misbehaviours, it
may demonstrate that network protocol
mechanisms can have impact in this space, if we
spend the time to try analyse the incentives of the
various parties.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="conclusions" title="Conclusions">
<t>At this stage we don't think it approriate to claim that any
strong conclusion can be reached based on the above. We do
however, claim that the is a topic that could be worth
discussion at the DEDR workshop and elsewhere.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>This draft is all about security, and privacy.
</t>
<t>Encryption is one of the most effective tools in countering network based
attackers and will also have a role in protecting against adversarial
applications. However, today many existing tools for countering adversarial
applications assume they can inspect network traffic to or from potentially
adversarial applications. These facts of course cause tensions (e.g. see
<xref target="RFC8404"/>).  Expanding our threat model could possibly help reduce some of
those tensions, if it leads to the development of protocols that make
exploitation harder or more transparent for adversarial applications.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>There are no IANA considerations.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>We'll happily ack anyone who's interested enough to read
and comment on this.
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-grease.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nottingham-for-the-users.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1984.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2404.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6962.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7258.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8240.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8404.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"?>
<reference anchor="cambridge" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=8436400">
<front>
    <title>User Data Privacy: Facebook, Cambridge Analytica, and Privacy Protection</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Isaak" fullname="Jim Isaak"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Hanna" fullname="Mina J. Hanna"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Computer" value="51.8 (2018): 56-59"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="curated" target="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~seal/publications/2018ICSE_Hammad.pdf">
<front>
    <title>A large-scale empirical study on the effects of code obfuscations on Android apps and anti-malware products</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Hammad" fullname="Mahmoud Hammad"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="Garcia" fullname="Joshua Garcia"/>
    <author initials="S." surname="MaleK" fullname="Sam Malek"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="ACM International Conference on Software Engineering" value="2018"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="mailbug" target="https://www.degruyter.com/downloadpdf/j/popets.2018.2018.issue-1/popets-2018-0006/popets-2018-0006.pdf">
<front>
    <title>I never signed up for this! Privacy implications of email tracking</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Englehardt" fullname="Steven Englehardt"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="Han" fullname="Jeffrey Han"/>
    <author initials="A." surname="Narayanan" fullname="Arvind Narayanan"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Proceedings on Privacy Enhancing Technologies" value="2018.1 (2018): 109-126."/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="smarttv" target="https://www.ndss-symposium.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/eurousec2018_16_Malkin_paper.pdf">
<front>
    <title>“What Can’t Data Be Used For?” Privacy Expectations about Smart TVs in the U.S.</title>
    <author initials="N." surname="Malkin" fullname="Nathan Malkin"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="Bernd" fullname="Julia Bernd"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Johnson" fullname="Maritza Johnson"/>
    <author initials="S." surname="Egelman" fullname="Serge Egelman"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="European Workshop on Usable Security (Euro USEC)" value="2018"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="toys" target="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1805.02751.pdf">
<front>
    <title>Security and Privacy Analyses of Internet of Things Childrens' Toys</title>
    <author initials="G." surname="Chu" fullname="Gordon Chu"/>
    <author initials="N." surname="Apthorpe" fullname="Noah Apthorpe"/>
    <author initials="N." surname="Feamster" fullname="Nick Feamster"/> 
    <date year="2019"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="IEEE Internet of Things Journal" value="6.1 (2019): 978-985."/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="tracking" target="https://scholarspace.manoa.hawaii.edu/bitstream/10125/50485/paper0598.pdf">
<front>
    <title>Web Tracking-A Literature Review on the State of Research</title>

    <author initials="T." surname="Ermakova" fullname="Tatiana Ermakova">
        <organization>University of Potsdam</organization>
        <address>
            <email>tatiana.ermakova@uni-potsdam.de</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Fabian" fullname="Benjamin Fabian">
        <organization>HfT Leipzig</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Bender" fullname="Benedict Bender">
        <organization>University of Potsdam</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Klimek" fullname="Kerstin Klimek">
        <organization>University of Potsdam</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of the 51st Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="unread" target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2018.1486870">
<front>
    <title>The biggest lie on the internet: Ignoring the privacy policies and terms of service policies of social networking services</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Obar" fullname="Jonathan A. Obar"/>
    <author initials="A." surname="Oeldorf-Hirsch" fullname="Anne Oeldorf-Hirsch"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Information, Communication and Society" value="(2018): 1-20"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="vpns" target="https://eprints.networks.imdea.org/1886/1/imc18-final198.pdf">
<front>
    <title> An empirical analysis of the commercial VPN ecosystem</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Khan" fullname="Mohammad Taha Khan"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="DeBlasio" fullname="Joe DeBlasio"/>
    <author initials="G." surname="Voelker" fullname="Geoffrey M. Voelker"/>
    <author initials="A." surname="Snoeren" fullname="Alex C. Snoeren"/>
    <author initials="C." surname="Kanich" fullname="Chris Kanich"/>
    <author initials="N." surname="Vallina-Rodrigue" fullname="Narseo Vallina-Rodriguez"/>
    <date year="2018"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="ACM Internet Measurement Conference" value="2018 (pp. 443-456)"/>
</reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
